Hi, this is going to be another
follow-up video on this vintage Sony
CCD camcorder that I've torn down in a
couple of previous videos because I
wanted to have a look at the delay lines
used in these PAL uh
camcorders. Now, we had a a delay line
in the video head, if you remember, this
was the board from the video head. If
you haven't seen the video, if you're
coming in late to the game, uh the link
will be down below where we tore this
down. Now, this has a delay line in it,
and you can see the delay line there,
and I've found the service manual for
this thing, so I know exactly what the
delay in that thing is. So, uh we'll
have a look at that in a minute, but I
thought we'd actually have a look at
these delay lines, see
um how they work because I think we've
got a couple of different types here in
this camcorder. This one's in the video
head, and the other one is in the video
8 uh tape transport system here. And if
you flip if we flip it over, there's the
other delay line down in there, which is
saw in uh the first teardown as well.
And
you can see that they're physically
different types. This one is long and
cylindrical like this, and this one is
flat and, you know, almost like a well,
surface mounty um and a large form
factor like that. So, they're clearly
operating on different principles. So, I
thought we'd uh have a look at how delay
lines work, and maybe see if we can
crack these things open cuz I think
these two will work on different
principles. Could be interesting. Let's
go. And just a follow-up to that uh
microscope thing I had in the previous
video, I won't explain it again. You
have to watch the previous one if you
haven't seen it. Um
a couple of people suggested that it
might be a polarizing filter on the
front of the um CCD sensor. Well, it's
not and I've got the uh chip in the
other orientation now to where it was
last time and I can rotate it
around. I've got to be careful.
Here we go. I'll rotate it all the way
around to where we saw it last time.
And
bingo. You can see that it's still
exactly
the same. So, it's not anything to do
with the polarization filter.
And check this out. I've got my finger
about uh 30 a good 30 cm away from that
eyepiece, the second eyepiece down in
here of the microscope, the one that's
uh getting all the light. And of course,
if I turn off my ambient lights here in
the lab, bang, that's all It hasn't
quite vanished cuz I have got my ring
light uh turned on around the base of it
down there. But if I turn the
my main lights back on, hello,
remote control,
there we go.
About 30 My finger's about 30 cm away
and you can see the image
of my finger
in the field of view through the light
being reflected through this eyepiece
down onto the chip and back out. If If
that was a wider field of view, I could
do like cute little bunny rabbits and
hand puppet and shadow puppetry there.
But that is That is cool. I like that.
Now, check this out. What I've done is
I've folded the tape transport
system like this completely open that we
didn't see before in the uh previous
tear down and I've got the delay this
that second delay line. There it is
under there and there's a whole bunch of
other stuff under there we didn't uh we
didn't see. But this thing it looks like
it's designed to operate even when it's
like completely folded out like that. I
think I should be able to power this
thing up and uh uh
and put the tape in and then be able to
probe the delay line on the bottom and
probe other stuff and well,
let's give it a go. So,
you only need the uh
battery power coming in and that's it.
And if I switch it on,
yep,
we've got our tape counter on there.
The tape transport system is going.
If I press eject,
sorry you can't see that. I probably
should uh
whack the camera around the other way,
but there we go. It's out.
Put the tape in and
not a problem. It's playing and counting
up. Look at that.
Brilliant. The whole thing operates
while it's completely unfolded.
Ah.
Beautiful bit of systems engineering
that, just beautiful. Well, I've got in
there and probed the delay line in
there, all eight pins. This is an
eight-pin
delay line in there and I'm getting
nothing on any of the pins at all when
this thing is
uh when this thing is playing. So,
um I don't think that delay line is used
at all. Perhaps it's used for the
recording
function instead of the uh
instead of the playback function,
perhaps. And there's our second delay
line in there. You can see it's an
eight-pin
device and it's a glass It's you know,
it's made by
what? Asahi Glass Co. So, it's most
likely a glass-based
delay line, uh I would be assuming. Very
complex bit
of system engineering, really. Really is
quite
quite amazing and it works when it's all
folded out, thanks to those hinge
connectors,
those Sony hinge connectors down in
there. that uh work brilliantly. They
don't have to be uh folded, of course,
because they've got the metal uh going
right through there regardless of
whether or not they're open or closed.
So, there you go. That is
one neat bit of gear. I really like it.
Really designed for servicing. I'm
certainly getting information. I'll show
you on the scope in a second.
From this pin,
I presume that's going in, but I'm
getting nothing
on
the other pin. So, this looks like
something's going in, but nothing's
coming out. So, there it is. That That's
what's uh going in there.
And
if we have a look at that, we can
can certainly
see that there's information
going in there. We can capture that and
and zoom in on that, but there's
certainly something going in.
And you can see some drift there as
well.
Now, if we turn the intensity down,
you can see data
moving back and forth there. Sort of
that analog
video data moving around. That That'd be
the individual line data, I would
presume.
It's jumping around the place there, but
uh it doesn't seem to be uh I presume
that's the input to the delay line, and
there doesn't seem to be anything else
coming out. Strange. I was able to
download the service manual for this
particular camcorder, the CCD-V8AF,
and check out the date there, October
1985.
And you can see the amount of work that
went into this thing in 1985. I mean,
you know, this is pretty much uh
predates the desktop publishing Well,
you know, almost predates the desktop
publishing thing where producing
documents like this is, you know, it
it's still a lot of work these days, but
imagine what it was like back then.
Just, you know,
serious amount of work. Look at all
these hand-drawn
diagrams that have gone in here showing
you how to disassemble each and every
nut and screw on the thing. It's just
It's absolutely crazy.
So, in addition to all these beautiful
hand-drawn diagrams, they've also got
internal photos as well inside the thing
pointing out every aspect, every
individual part showing you all the
boards flipped open. And then, we get
down into some more
uh exploded view stuff. And then, whoa,
check this out, folks. Look at this.
Uh see if I can get this whole thing on
here. I've got to zoom right out. There
it is.
We have a block diagram of the whole
complete system operation. And check out
this down here. This whole operational
block diagram complete with waveforms
and everything else spread across
multiple pages.
Ah. It's a thing of beauty and a joy
forever. Look at this. I mean, you know,
you just don't get service manuals like
this Well, anymore Well, you do. I mean,
there's still service manuals for
commercial stuff, but, you know, I don't
know if they're this good anymore. I
mean, this is just phenomenal stuff. And
we haven't even, you know, we're still
at the block system block diagram level
separated into separate boards and
everything like that. And it looks like
we're finally getting down into No,
that's more block diagram. We'll
probably eventually get down into the
actual schematics.
More block diagrams. There's our CRT
viewfinder. So, excellent. We've got the
schematic for our CRT viewfinder. So,
that'll be another separate video. And
we eventually get down into Look at
this. I mean, it's just
It's phenomenal. Look at all the
waveform
diagrams over here for all the points.
And then we're getting down into overlay
diagrams of all the boards. I just
I love this. Look at this. Here we go.
It looks like we've got some real
schematics now.
But the schematics don't necessarily
interest us. You can see the when
they've scanned this document and you
can see all the the page behind that
unfortunately, but it's still very, very
clear and
Yeah, that's fantastic. I mean, just the
amount of work which went into producing
these service manuals. I'd love to know
how many people worked on it and how
long it took them to do this in 1985.
It'd be hard enough to do it today. If
you've ever produced documentation for
stuff, you'll know what I'm talking
about. And these are all foldout
diagrams, folks. These are all I can't
even get them
all completely on the screen capture
here. And so these are all foldout
diagrams. This service manual would have
been worth its weight in gold. And
here's all the detailed schematics.
You've got to be kidding me.
This is great. I could just scroll
through this all day long. I love it.
And check out this schematic here of
what looks like the audio board. And
look, not only have they done the
schematic and showing you the chip, but
they've also showing you the internal
operation of the chip, test point
voltages all the way around this thing
and and the flow and the signal flow
directions as well. Line in, mute, line
out, VCO, all that. It's just
It's fantastic.
My hat's off to whoever has put together
this service manual. And yeah, their uh
names are long forgotten, I'm sure, but
how much work went in? Man, it's just
incredible.
So, let's try and find our delay lines
within this uh
block huge block diagram view. Uh the
waveforms, look at uh it's it's it's
just beautiful.
Uh
I love it. Anyway, here we go. We're at
the uh video transport uh system over
here, and you can see the drum. There's
the video head, and uh well, the two
video heads, and there's the amplifiers
for the video heads, and all the
miscellaneous circuitry for all that.
We've got some traps in here.
Uh limiters, all sorts of stuff, and
it's it's a little bit hard to uh
follow, of course, cuz this is these
systems are incredibly complex. I you
know,
I mean, the amount of
um
effort which went into not only
designing these systems, but you know,
designing the PAL standard to begin
with, and NTSC, and all those other
standards, they're incredibly
complex. But, I guess they they had to
do it at the time because digital really
wasn't in then. So, they had to do all
this stuff in analog. But, anyway, if we
uh
muck around here, here we go. Let's have
a look. Bingo.
There it is. DL101
2H delay there. Now, um
I don't have any further specs on that,
but it would almost uh certainly be the
64 microsecond
uh line
64 microsecond delay line used in well,
standard in uh these PAL systems cuz it
had to delay a complete line of
information. That's what the PAL
standard required in other in order to
get the color
uh right, and technical details like
that. You can go look up the PAL
standard and PAL operation if you want
to know more about that, but it requires
All these PAL systems require a 64
microsecond delay line, and there it is
down in there, and that does
uh the component designated DL101
matches up. So, that's our delay line,
and that will most certainly be 64
microseconds. And if we look closer, we
can actually see here's DL101 up here,
but there's also DL102
down here, and let's try and find the
other one, which was on the camera
system. So, if you look at the camera
system block diagram here, I mean,
there's all sorts of stuff in here.
Check this out. We got
signal separation. This is the process
control IC. We've got all sorts of
clamps and offsets and white balance
adjustments and white clipping and
pedestal stuff for the uh waveform. It
shows you all the detail waveforms at
each particular point in the in the
system. Here's the CCD imager around
here, and there you go. There's that uh
clock driver that we saw with that uh
TTL-to-MOS clock driver there driving
the clocks for the CCD imager. There's
the output. There's a buffer there, and
there's the two other uh MOS uh
TTL-to-MOS uh drivers we saw on that
board as well uh to generate the timing
for the CCD sensor. There's a little
clock board with its low-pass filter and
its
oscillator. And then we've got a uh sync
generator all over here, and ah man,
this is, you know, all over white
balance
uh control IC.
It's all happening, but let's try and
find um That looks complex as well.
There's more pedestal stuff, and
ah white balance set.
Ah, this is crazy. Look at all the work
that goes into
producing
What are these PAL signals? It's just ah
processing them. It's crazy. Anyway,
ta-da! Here it is. DL701.
It's a 0.18 microsecond or 180
nanosecond delay line, and that's much
smaller than 64 microseconds. There are
big technology differences required in
in producing these two types of delay
lines with these values. Now, 180
nanoseconds isn't that much at all, so
you can produce that with just a
basically a big coil of wire, pretty
much a big length of wire, because you
know, the propagation delay roughly, you
know, 15 cm per nanosecond or some, you
know, near enough to that sort of rule
of thumb. So, you can work out what
length wire you need to delay that
signal by 180 nanoseconds. So, I think
if we crack open DL701, which is with
the slim white one we saw there, then
that one is going to be a resistive
delay line or just an electrical delay
line, as they call them. So, there won't
be anything fancy physically in there. I
think we'll just get a big coil of wire,
and that's it. But, the other one, the
64 microsecond one, that requires a
different technology again, because you
can't get the length of wire required in
there to give a 64 microsecond delay.
So, that's going to use a different
technology, either glass
sort of glass piezo-ceramic type
technology. So, that one will be very
physically physically very interesting
if we're able to crack it open.
And I managed to find the delay lines
here on the actual schematic itself.
Here's IC102,
and here's delay line 102 down here, and
here's delay line 101 up the top here.
So, um we were getting a signal on one
of those pins there, but we certainly
weren't getting it on the other pin. So,
I am
I don't know. I could analyze this and
look through this whole thing all day
long, but I don't think I'm going to
bother. The object of a delay line is to
delay the signal by that 64 microseconds
in this case. So, um
uh
I don't know why we're not seeing that
and I don't really care. I'm more
interested to see what's inside this
delay line.
And here's that Slimline 180
ns
delay line I pulled off the board here.
And we don't even have to take it apart.
Ta-da! There it is. Now, if you do the
rule of thumb math on this thing of one
uh nanosecond for uh every 150 mm of
wire, then really um
that works out to 27 m of wire. And
that's an awful lot. I
I suspect there's not 27 m of wire in
this thing. There are some surface mount
caps
sort of soldered between those
individual pins there.
And yep, there you go. I'm getting about
170 odd picofarads on that one there.
And yep, they're all about 170 odd
picofarads. So, we've got ourselves a uh
little LC
delay line here. So, this one is clearly
not as simple as just a uh resistive
uh wire delay line that we assumed at
first glance. So, what we have here is
in effect your traditional
uh multi-stage LC delay line. Uh usually
they're multi-tapped. You can actually
get them as a multi-tapped chips and
things like that, but this is obviously
not a uh semiconductor-based one. This
is a you know, it's got real 170
picofarad capacitors in there. It's got
real inductors, but
um usually
they of course will have an input and
output and a ground pin, and this one
does actually have three pins on it. So,
I traced this sucker out here, and this
is what we have. We have uh four
inductors there. You can see them wound
on there like that, and we have one
common pin with 370 picofarad uh caps.
These um
inner ones are about 33 to 37
microhenries each. The two outer ones,
24 microhenries each. And that is pretty
much all she wrote. And if we hook up
our delay line here, what I've got is
the uh
uh all of the ground leads connected to
the uh ground point of of the delay
line. I'm feeding in a 10 kHz square
wave, uh which is the yellow waveform
here, and the green waveform is the
output. And you can see the delay there,
you know, it's got lots of ringing on
it. That you know, I haven't terminated
it properly, so forget about that. We
just want you know, we're not going for
super super fidelity here. So, let's
just
put this here, and let's measure
that difference there. We've got
uh 20 nanoseconds per division. 20 40 60
80 100 120 140 160. So, we're you know,
near about the 180, the claimed 180
nanosecond delay time
on this thing. So, you know, if we if we
measured this properly, I'm sure we'd
might get a bit more accurate, but there
you go. That is your delay right there
with your LC filter. So, that is a good
example of a classic passive LC
uh multi-stage filter. Let's go and
check out the uh other one, the I think
it's going to be like a glass uh
substrate. You won't find any wires and
capacitors inside this other one. Let's
go have a peek.
Now, here's the delay line I've
desoldered from the circuit. It's going
to be a glass-based
one sort of but it looks like it's a
sealed
package. So, um but it it I don't think
it will actually be potted inside
because these have to work on um you
know, physical properties. Um the
physical vibrational wave properties.
So, um if you pot these things, um they
may not work as intended. So, I'm hoping
that we can crack this thing open and uh
see inside of it. You won't find any
circuitry inside here, folks. It'll be
just some basic physics.
And I've managed to cut off one side of
it there and you can see what looks like
the glass
substrate
inside of that thing. So, I'll keep uh
hacking around this and see if I can get
that top cover to pop off and uh
we'll be able to see the whole thing.
And here you go, folks. This is what is
inside one of these glass delay lines.
And we're going to have a bunch of
interesting physics in here. As I said,
there's no components. There's just the
four wires going over there under the
bottom side of this plate which this one
would have been specifically tweaked for
that 65 64 microseconds
for that one line of the PAL signal. So,
I'm going to see if I can lift this out
and pop it over and see what's on the
other side.
Nothing on the other side except another
one of these uh
just one of these um little
uh isolation pads. I don't know what
they're actually doing. Probably uh
isolating the thing vibrational-wise,
but the back of the plate here has these
marks on them. Found that this material
here is almost certainly a quartz uh
glass and we've got two transducers and
this basically is a very common very
typical
uh or sometimes called an ultrasonic or
a piezoelectric or glass delay line.
Now, what's happened here is we've got
two transducers here, one here and one
here and presumably you can drive them
either direction. I'm not entirely sure
about that, but basically we've got a
piezoelectric transducer and these
little pads in here, these are dampeners
which effectively guide the signal
around.
It's rather fascinating. I
I really like it. So, these
these dampeners on the bottom here,
they've
they're clear like I'm not you know,
it's looks like they've just dobbed on
some uh
you know, some sort of um epoxy type
stuff, but maybe that's all that's
needed to effectively change the uh
surface or the acoustic wave and the
acoustic wave properties of the material
at that point and the waves actually
travel around them in some convoluted
pattern and back out again and that's
what causes the delay because it takes
time for these uh acoustic waves to
travel through this material. I
Ah, man.
It's really quite neat. I love physics
like this, but to get into it, I'm sure
it is actually very very advanced stuff.
The person who came up with this in the
first place, genius. Now, if we have a
close look at this, we can actually
follow the path. You'll note the note
the two transducers here separated by a
dampening pad in there and either side.
So, that means the signal comes in and
out of that little gap in there between
those dampening pads. Now, if we have a
look at it, let's assume that we put our
signal into these two wires over here,
then it's going to emit out of here. The
acoustic signal is then going to travel
straight down here, bounce off the end
because you're going to get a you know,
some sort of end effect on that. It's
going to reflect just like
um similar effect to say a light inside
a fiber optic tube for example, and then
it's going to bounce off there, bounce
off this wall, off that one, all the way
through here, bounce off here, here, all
the way back across here, off that one,
down there, bounce, bounce, and bam, out
that transducer there.
Neat. And there's a close-up shot of the
two transducers there. Now,
unfortunately, I don't know
anything more about the physics and the
operation of this, even though I do have
a background in
piezoceramic transducers. This is
obviously not a ceramic base one. This
is a quartz glass base one. But, if
anyone has any interest in
papers or you know, stuff on how these
things
actually work, then please either link
them in the comments or
jump on over to the EV blog forum and
link them over there and discuss it cuz
this is a real interesting topic and
these are a fairly rare these days
because we don't have analog systems or
too many analog systems left that
require these sort sorts of things. They
used to be used in you know, power
video, which we basically
don't have much of anymore. Everything's
gone digital. We used to have delay
lines in audio systems, but they've gone
the way of the dodo since pretty much
since the advent of every you know,
audio's all gone digital. And uh these
are you know,
getting rarer and rarer, but these used
to be very common components back in the
pre-digital days. I love it. So, I hope
you enjoyed that quick look at delay
lines. And if you like the video, please
give it a big thumbs up cuz that helps a
lot.
Catch you next time.